Saurabh Prakash

Bengaluru. +91-9686608315. isaurabhprakash@gmail.com. linkedin.com/isaurabhprakash. github.com/isaurabhprakash

Experienced developer with a thirst for knowledge and a love of problem-solving. Consistently recognized for delivering high-quality code on time and budget. Worked on creating an Object-Oriented Database for premise systems. Agile Learner with Success Across Multiple Projects.

Key hard skills include:

C++| OOPS | Design Thinking | Git | OODB | Mentoring | Debugging | Unit Testing | Project Planning

Experience

Associate Staff Engineer

Oct 2022 - Present

Tally Solutions Pvt. Ltd.

- Owning the delivery of the TallyPlugin framework, which enables the seamless delivery of select features developed by Tally Solutions to specific customers, contributing to enhanced customer satisfaction and product functionality.
- Led a team of 5 developers in the development of TallyPlugin, maintaining constant communication with Product Managers (PM) and Quality Assurance (QA) team, and facilitating cross-functional collaboration as needed for the project. Additionally, conducted regular scrum meetings for the Plugin, ensuring efficient coordination and progress tracking within the team.
- As the lead developer in the flagship GST Release of the product, I spearheaded efforts across various critical areas, leveraging in-depth functional and technical knowledge, thus contributing to making it the highest-adopted release of the company in 40 years.
- Conducted thorough analysis to identify bottlenecks affecting the product's speed, leading to the redesign of the in-house OODB filesystem for improved performance.
- Served as a mentor of 2 people in the organisation, while also acting as a guide for multiple interns

Senior Software Development Engineer

Apr 2021 - Oct 2022

Tally Solutions Pvt. Ltd.

- Played a pivotal role as a key contributor in the GST Release of the product, ensuring its successful deployment and functionality.
- Took ownership of the Purpose Data sub-module, a critical component facilitating data exchange with third parties. This
 module provided a multitude of capabilities including versioning, reconciliation, storage of third-party data, and
 transaction history.
- Participated in making the UI Reports faster by implementing on-disk structures that can be used to store and retrieve data faster

Software Development Engineer - II

Apr 2020 - Mar 2021

Tally Solutions Pvt. Ltd.

- Did system design, code design, implementation, and component testing of a data sync component based on the hub & spoke model, facilitating data exchange over the network.
- Contributed to enhancing user experience by implementing changes to enable Dynamic Company Context change, allowing seamless transition of the product context from any screen.
- Enhanced the filesystem's functionality by re-implementing a Range-tree-based file indexing, which was crucial for enabling concurrent operations on the filesystem.
- Made significant contributions to improving the speed of the overall database system by implementing partial read-and-write optimisation.
- Rectified the build configuration of the in-house build tool Maya for several components.

Software Development Engineer - I

Jul 2018 - Mar 2020

Tally Solutions Pvt. Ltd.

- Achieved 100% unit test coverage of the filesystem layer, a milestone for the organisation.
- Identified and resolved various bugs within the filesystem, both in legacy and newly integrated code.
- Simplified the filesystem's structure and removed unnecessary dependencies, enhancing its overall maintainability and reliability.

Education

B.E, Computer Science and Engineering

2014 - 2018

Sir M. Visvesvaraya Institute of Technology, Bengaluru

Aggr: 78 % First Class with Distinction in all the semesters

Computer AISSCE (Class XII), PCM

2012 - 2014

Bijendra Public School, Purnea

Percentage: 89 %

Recognitions

Impact Player AMJ 2022

Given yearly to one person in the entire engineering function for:

- Ownership and result orientation in ensuring the completeness, correctness and overall quality of design of components/ features.
- Ownership and result orientation in ensuring that work happens with high quality and as per the plan
- Bringing absolute transparency during the journey into product releases, so that corrective action can be taken to ensure the flawlessness and usefulness of our product.

Start of the Quarter AMJ 2022

Given quarterly to one person in the entire engineering function for demonstrating:

- Significant impact by way of technical solutions
- Creating considerable impact through demonstrated mastery in our domain, technology or
- software engineering process
- Significant improvement in quality and/or outcome of the product

Super Coder 2021 - 2022

Given yearly to one person in the entire engineering function for demonstrating:

- Well-thought-out code design and code
- Elegance in code, good code smell
- Zero (or near zero) defects in the outcome
- Good coverage of Non-functional aspects

Rookie of the Year 2019-2020

Given to one person in the entire engineering function with less than 2 years of experience:

- Showing exceptional outcome and dedication in gaining mastery over the area of work
- Demonstrating the ability to solve complex problems independently
- Putting in extra effort in completing a critical part of the work

Extra-Curricular Activities

Trained the batch of 2023 in Diagnostics in Software Development

- Trained the batch of 2022 in Object Oriented Database
- Trained the batch of 2020 in C++, Data Structures, and Algorithms training to the batch 2020.
- . Created a diagnostic tool used across the organization
- Officially mentored several Software Engineering Intern on different projects which included creating an OODB with proper file indexes in C++ and creating a standalone application that can communicate with WhatsApp
- Officially mentored 2 people in the organization for their overall development.
- Being a member of the employee engagement group, organized multiple programs for the organization including the annual football and badminton league.
- Core member of the team that conducted the first nationwide hackathon by the organization